Charles Ewing Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charles Ewing Family Papers 1769-1951 (bulk 1850-1890)
MSS20073
Ewing, Charles, 1835-1883
9,000 items
30 containers plus 1 oversize
12.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer and army officer. Correspondence, diaries, biographical material, genealogical notebooks, legal and business papers, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, and other papers relating to the family of Charles Ewing during and after the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Anderson, Virginia Miller Ewing, 1875-1966--Correspondence.; Arnold, Samuel, 1834-1906--Trials, litigation, etc.; Browning, Orville Hickman, 1806-1881.; Clarke, Luke, -1881--Correspondence.; Daly, Kathleen Ewing, 1884-1971--Correspondence.; Denman, Hampton B., 1830-1895--Correspondence.; Ewing family.; Ewing, Charles, 1835-1883.; Ewing, Charles, 1835-1883.; Ewing, Charles, 1835-1883. Charles Ewing papers. 1777-1941.; Ewing, Charles, 1872-1954--Correspondence.; Ewing, Hugh, 1826-1905.; Ewing, James Gillespie Blaine, 1880-1965--Correspondence.; Ewing, John Krepps Miller, 1878-1960--Correspondence.; Ewing, Maria, 1877-1958--Correspondence.; Ewing, Philemon, 1820-1896--Correspondence.; Ewing, Thomas, 1789-1871. Thomas Ewing papers. 1834-1949.; Ewing, Thomas, 1829-1896--Correspondence.; Ewing, Thomas, 1829-1896.; Ewing, Virginia Larwill Miller, 1846-1937. Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing papers. 1865-1951.; Larwill family.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Assassination.; Lusk, Charles S. (Charles Stoner), 1851-1928--Correspondence.; Miller family.; Sherman, Ellen Ewing, 1824-1888--Correspondence.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891.; Steele, Clement F.; Steele, Clement F.--Correspondence.; Steele, Maria Theresa Ewing, 1837- --Correspondence.; Stibbs family.; Washington, Reade M., 1850-1922--Correspondence.; Wolfley, Lewis, 1839-1910--Correspondence.
Organizations
Ewing & Hunter.; Ewing & Jackson.; United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Office of Indian Affairs.
Subjects
Amnesty--United States.; Cotton trade--United States.; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry.; Genealogy.; Indians of North America--Government relations.; Land grants.; Land tenure--Kansas--Leavenworth.; Land tenure.; Pardon--United States.; Patents--United States.; Practice of law--Missouri--Saint Louis.; Practice of law--Washington (D.C.); Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)
Places
Leavenworth (Kan.)--Commerce.; Mexico--Claims.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Claims.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Social life and customs--19th century.; United States--Social life and customs--20th century.
Occupations
Army officers.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The Charles Ewing Family Papers were given to the Library of Congress in 1954 by John Krepps Miller Ewing and Eleanor Sherman Ewing. Additional material was transferred from the Exchange and Gift Division in 1968.
Additional Guides
The Charles Ewing Family Papers were described in a press release issued by the Library of Congress on June 25, 1954, and in the Library of Congress Information Bulletin 13, no. 26 (June 28, 1954): 3.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the Thomas Ewing Family Papers and the William T. Sherman Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The Charles Ewing Family Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Thomas Ewing (1789-1871)
Date Event
1789, Dec. 28 Born near West Liberty, Ohio County, Va.
1792 Moved with family to Marietta, Ohio
1798 Moved with family to Ames Township, Athens County, Ohio
1809 1812 Worked intermittently at the Kanawha, Va., saltworks
1812 1815 Attended Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
1815 1816 Studied law in the office of Philemon Beecher, Lancaster, Ohio; admitted to the bar in 1816
circa 1817 1822 Prosecuting attorney, Fairfield County, Ohio
1820 Married Maria Wills Boyle (died 1864)
1829 Adopted William T. Sherman
1830 Elected from Ohio, United States Senate
1841 Appointed secretary of the treasury; resigned Sept. 11
1849 1850 Appointed to organize the Home Department (later Department of the Interior) and served as the first secretary of the interior
1850 Appointed to the United States Senate to complete unexpired term of Thomas Corwin who became secretary of the treasury
1851 Retired from public service, resuming his law practice
1851 1869 Practiced law, largely before the United States Supreme Court
1861 Appointed delegate to the Peace Convention, Washington, D.C.
1868 Appointed secretary of war; United States Senate did not act on nomination
1871, Oct. 26 Died, Lancaster, Ohio
Thomas Ewing (1829-1896)
Date Event
1829, Aug. 7 Born, Lancaster, Ohio
1852 1854 Attended Brown University, Providence, R.I.
1854 1857 Lived in Cincinnati, Ohio; attended Cincinnati Law School; admitted to bar in 1855
1856 Married Ellen Ewing Cox
1857 circa 1862 Moved to Leavenworth, Kans., where he practiced law in the firm Ewing, Denman & Company with his brother, Hugh, and brothers-in-law, Hampton B. Denman and William T. Sherman; firm became Sherman, Ewing & McCook in 1859
1858 Member, Kansas Constitutional Convention
1861 Appointed delegate to Peace Convention, Washington, D.C. Served as first chief justice, Kansas Supreme Court; resigned 1862
1862 Brevetted major-general, United States Army; resigned 1865
1865 Defended Samuel Arnold, Edward Spangler, and Samuel Mudd on charges of conspiracy to assassinate Abraham Lincoln
1865 1870 Practiced law with Ewing & Browning, Washington, D.C.
1870 Moved to Lancaster, Ohio
1877 1881 Elected from Ohio, United States House of Representatives
1882 Moved to Yonkers, New York
1882 1896 Practiced law, New York, N.Y.
1896, Jan. 21 Died New York, N.Y.
Charles Ewing (1835-1883)
Date Event
1835, Mar. 6 Born, Lancaster, Ohio
circa 1850 circa 1854 Attended St. Joseph's College, Perry County, Ohio, and Gonzaga University, Washington, D.C.
1856 1858 Attended University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.
1860 Bachelor of laws, Cincinnati College, Cincinnati, Ohio Admitted to the bar, St. Louis, Mo.
1861 Entered United States Army with rank of captain
1863 1867 Served under his brother-in-law, William T. Sherman, and was part of the "March to the Sea"
1865 Brevetted colonel Promoted to brigadier-general in charge of volunteers; resigned in 1867
1867 1883 Practiced law, Washington, D.C.
1869 Admitted to bar of the United States Supreme Court
1870 Married Virginia Larwill Miller (died 1937)
1874 1883 Served as Catholic commissioner of Indian missions; became Bureau of Catholic Indian Missions in 1874
1883, June 20 Died, Washington, D.C.
Hugh Ewing
Date Event
1826, Oct. 31 Born, Lancaster, Ohio
1848 Entered United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.; resigned before graduation
1854 1856 Admitted to the bar and practiced law, St. Louis, Mo.
1857 1861 Moved to Leavenworth, Kans., where he practiced law in the firm Ewing, Denman & Company with his brother, Thomas, and brothers-in-law, Hampton B. Denman and William T. Sherman; firm became Sherman, Ewing & McCook in 1859; speculated in lands, roads, and government housing
1858 Married Henrietta Young (died 1927)
1861 Entered United States Army with rank of major
1862 Promoted to brigadier-general of volunteers
1865 Brevetted major-general of volunteers; resigned in 1866
1866 1870 Served as minister to Holland
1870 circa 1875 Practiced law, Washington, D.C.
circa 1875 Moved to Lancaster, Ohio
1905, June 30 Died near Lancaster, Ohio
Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing
Date Event
1846 Born, Mt. Vernon, Ohio
1870 Married Charles Ewing (died 1883)
1937, Oct. 21 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles Ewing Family Papers span the years 1769-1951, with the bulk of the material dating from 1850 to 1890. Before arriving at the Library of Congress, the papers had been arranged into a series of notebooks labeled with the name of the person to whom they pertained. The notebooks are organized into into the following series: Thomas Ewing (1789-1871) Papers, Charles Ewing (1835-1883) Papers, Genealogical File, Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing Papers, Miscellany, and Oversize.
The Thomas Ewing (1789-1871) Papers largely consist of records from the Washington, D.C., law office he operated with Orville Hickman Browning and later joined by his son Thomas Ewing (1829-1886). Included are legal cases involving courts martial and land claims. A group of correspondence relates to legal cases handled by Browning. The chronological file of Thomas Ewing (1829-1886) consists of documents relating to business and land transactions largely in Leavenworth, Kansas, by Thomas and his brother Hugh, legal cases involving pardons and amnesty after the Civil War, claims against the military and for restoration of property, land claims, and a set of notes written circa 1865 concerning Ewing's representation of Samuel Arnold, a coconspirator in the assassination of Abraham Lincoln. The scrapbooks, containing memorabilia, articles and clippings, land plats, commissions, and legal and personal correspondence relating to Thomas Ewing (1789-1871), were compiled by a family member.
The Charles Ewing (1835-1883) Papers consist of a diary, military records, correspondence, scrapbooks, and records relating to the law offices of Ewing & Hunter in St. Louis, Missouri, and Ewing & Jackson in Washington, D.C. The papers relate to the Civil War and its aftermath, especially the military circle formed by brothers Charles, Thomas, and Hugh Ewing, and their brothers-in-law, William T. Sherman and Clement F. Steele. The diary covers Ewing's service in the United States Army during the Civil War and his law career after the war. During the Civil War, Ewing served under Sherman, and was part of the Atlanta Campaign that included the "March to the Sea." The correspondence is mostly with family including Hampton B. Denman, Hugh Ewing, Philemon Ewing, Thomas Ewing (1829-1886), Ellen Ewing Sherman, William T. Sherman, Clement F. Steele, Maria Theresa Ewing Steele, and nieces and nephews. Other correspondents include Luke Clarke, Charles S. Lusk, Reade M. Washington, and Lewis Wolfley. Clarke and Wolfley had served with Ewing during the Civil War while Lusk served as Ewing's clerk at the Bureau of Catholic Indian Missions and later became its commissioner. The records of Ewing & Hunter consist of a letterpress book and letters received. The records of Ewing & Jackson include cases involving courts martial and other military claims, land grant claims, Office of Indian Affairs claims, Mexican claims, cotton claims after the Civil War, patents, and legal matters relating to various companies. The scrapbooks, relating to Ewing, his father, and William T. Sherman, seem to have been compiled by a family member.
The Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing Papers are comprised of correspondence and scrapbooks. The correspondence is largely with members of her family, chiefly her children, and recounts family life, social events, family genealogy, and church activities. Correspondents include Virginia Miller Ewing Anderson, Kathleen Ewing Daly, Charles Ewing (1872-1954), James Gillespie Blaine Ewing, John Krepps Miller Ewing, and Maria Ewing. The scrapbooks were compiled by a family member.
The Miscellany contains a genealogical notebook on the Gillespie family similar in content to those found in the Genealogical File on the Stibbs, Larwill, and Miller families. Included also is a photograph album of Civil War army officers.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Thomas Ewing (1789-1871) Papers, 1834-1949
Charles Ewing (1835-1883) Papers, 1777-1941
Genealogical File, 1769-1857
Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing Papers, 1856-1951
Miscellany, 1865
Oversize, 1777-1941
Container List
- Thomas Ewing (1789-1871) Papers, 1834-1949 (Box 1-3)
  Scrapbooks, records of his Washington, D.C., law office, a chronological file related to Thomas Ewing (1829-1896), and other related material.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Scrapbook, 1834-1949 See also Container 16, Scrapbooks, Thomas Ewing (Box 1)
  - Law office records (Box 2)
    - Chronological file of Thomas Ewing (1829-1896), 1858-1881, undated, (16 folders) (Box 2)
    - Cases (Box 3)
      - In re Application of Cullins, undated (Box 3)
      - Black, Samuel, court martial, 1864, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - School Authorities v. Blackett, circa 1867 (Box 3)
      - Smith v. Lee, circa 1864 (Box 3)
      - Waring, John H., court martial, 1863 (Box 3)
      - Wiley v. Brown, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Orville Hickman Browning, 1863-1868 (Box 3)
- Charles Ewing (1835-1883) Papers, 1777-1941 (Box 4-16)
  Diary, memorabilia, military records, correspondence, records relating to his St. Louis, Mo., and Washington, D.C., law offices, and scrapbooks.
  - Diary (Box 4)
    - Original, 1859-1881, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Typescript, 1868-1882 (Box 4)
  - Military records, 1861-1867 See also Container 16, Scrapbooks, Charles Ewing, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - From Thomas Ewing (1829-1896), 1867-1883, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - To and from family (Box 5)
      - Index (Box 5)
      - 1850-1861, (4 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1861-1862, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1862-1866, (4 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1866-1873, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - From Charles S. Lusk, 1872-1882, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - From and concerning Luke Clarke, 1864-1874 (Box 8)
    - From and concerning Hampton B. Denman, 1867-1880 (Box 8)
    - From Hugh Ewing, 1867-1882 (Box 8)
    - From Jay Ewing, 1882 (Box 8)
    - From Philemon Ewing, 1867-1872 (Box 8)
    - From and concerning Reade M. Washington, 1867-1873 (Box 8)
    - From Lewis Wolfley, 1870-1882 (Box 8)
  - Law office records of Ewing & Jackson, Washington, D.C. (Box 9)
    - Cases (Box 9)
      - Armes, George A., restoration of military rank, 1867-1877 (Box 9)
      - Darling, John A., court martial, 1877 (Box 9)
      - Duryea, Richard C., court martial, 1870-1879 (Box 9)
      - Ely, George, court martial, 1864 (Box 9)
      - Fletcher, Bird L., court martial, 1872 (Box 9)
      - Gilman, J. H., court martial, 1872 (Box 9)
      - Glavis, George O., court martial, 1866 (Box 9)
      - Haller, Granville O., court martial, 1863-1879 (Box 9)
      - Inman, Henry, court martial, 1872-1877 (Box 9)
      - Jennison, Charles R., court martial, 1865 (Box 9)
      - Kirby, D. T., court martial, 1879 (Box 9)
      - Macklin, James E., court martial, 1876-1881 (Box 9)
      - Michaelis, Otho E., court martial, 1875 (Box 9)
      - Mills, Anson, court martial, 1871-1874 (Box 9)
      - Outlaw, Edward W., court martial and pardon, 1865-1866 (Box 9)
      - Rathbone, Henry R., leave of absence, 1864, 1878 (Box 9)
      - Schaumburg, James W., claims for army rank, 1877-1879 (Box 9)
      - Stanhope, P. W., court martial, 1868-1871 (Box 10)
      - Vedder, Nicholas, court martial, 1863, 1875-1877 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous military claims, 1869-1880 (Box 10)
      - Army officers dismissed and court martialed, lists, 1866-1876 (Box 10)
    - Other legal matters (Box 10)
      - East India Telegraph Co., 1867 (Box 10)
      - Federal Printing Co., assignment of Robert Finley Hunter, 1877-1878 (Box 10)
      - Grant Coal and Coal Oil and Lumber Co., Allegheny [Allegany] County, Md., 1875 (Box 10)
      - H. G. Cattle Ranch, Texas, undated (Box 10)
      - Lee Marble Co., Massachusetts, 1881-1883 (Box 10)
      - Mexican claims (Box 10)
        - Tehuantepec Transit Co., 1866-1867 (Box 10)
        - Texas claims against Mexico, 1866-1878 (Box 10)
      - Morris Island, South Carolina, undated (Box 10)
      - National Aquarium Association, Sandy Hook, N. J., 1879-1880 (Box 10)
    - United States land grant claims (Box 10)
      - Chauvin claim, St. Louis, Mo., 1863-1880 (Box 10)
      - Copen claim, Madison County, Ohio, 1868-1870 (Box 11)
      - Heirs of Pedro Armendoris, 1869-1873 (Box 11)
      - Heirs of John Kennedy, 1868-1869 (Box 11)
      - "P-R" miscellaneous, 1860-1869 (Box 11)
      - Union Pacific Railroad, 1867-1873 (Box 11)
      - Van Trump, P. Beecher, 1871 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous, 1867-1874 (Box 11)
    - Military claims (Box 11)
      - Paymaster general's office, 1873 (Box 11)
      - Surgeon general's office, 1878-1882 (Box 11)
      - United States Army (Box 11)
        - Pensions, 1871-1876 (Box 11)
        - Promotions, 1869-1881, (2 folders) (Box 11)
        - Retirements, 1869-1877 (Box 11)
    - Office of Indian Affairs claims, circa 1866-circa 1890 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
        - A-M, (20 folders) (Box 11)
        - N-W, (8 folders) (Box 12)
      - Tribes (Box 12)
        - Cherokee (Box 12)
        - Chippewa (Box 12)
        - Choctaw (Box 12)
        - Creek (Box 12)
        - Delaware (Box 12)
        - Miami (Box 12)
        - Osage, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 12, Box 13)
        - Ottawa (Box 13)
        - Seminole and other tribes (Box 13)
        - Shawnee, (2 folders) (Box 13)
        - Various tribes (Box 13)
    - Interior Department claims, 1870-1877 (Box 13)
  - Law office records of Ewing & Hunter, St. Louis, Mo. (Box 13)
    - Letterpress book, 1860 (Box 13)
    - Letters received, 1860-1861 (Box 13)
  - Law office records of Ewing & Jackson, Washington, D.C. (Box 14)
    - Cotton claims from Civil War (Box 14)
      - List of claimants in South Carolina and Georgia (Box 14)
      - Cases, circa 1866-circa 1884, (12 folders) (Box 14)
    - Patents and abstracts of patents, (8 folders) (Box 14)
    - Other claims (Box 14)
      - Barker, Essex 1872-1874 (Box 14)
      - Ingalls, Rufus, 1871-1878 (Box 14)
      - Simerly, Elijah, 1868-1869 (Box 14)
      - Various, 1866-1878 (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
        - A-B, (2 folders) (Box 14)
        - C-Y, (21 folders) (Box 15)
        - Unfiled material (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 16)
    - "Miscellaneous II" regarding William T. Sherman and the Society of the Army of Tennessee, circa 1869-circa 1881 (Box 16)
    - "Miscellaneous III" containing correspondence, receipts, envelopes, and clippings, circa 1859-circa 1882 (Box 16)
    - Charles Ewing (1835-1883), Thomas Ewing (1789-1871), and George Ewing (1754-1824), 1777-1941 See Oversize (Box 16)
- Genealogical File, 1769-1857 (Box 17-18)
  Notebooks of collected genealogical information including biographical notes, correspondence, charts, photographs, photostatic copies, and original documents regarding the ancestors of Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Stibbs family, 1769-1857 (Box 17)
  - Larwill family, 1807-1824, (2 vols.); (1 vol.) (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Miller family, circa 1804-1847, (2 vols.) (Box 18)
- Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing Papers, 1856-1951 (Box 18-29)
  Correspondence with family, chiefly her children, and scrapbooks.
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
    - Letters to and from family (Box 18)
      - Vol. 1, 1856-1874 (Box 18)
      - Vols. 2-3, 1874-1883 (Box 19)
      - Vols. 4-6, 1882-1925 (Box 20)
      - Vols. 7-8, 1892-1896 (Box 21)
      - Vols. 9-11, 1897-1901 (Box 22)
      - Vols. 12-14, 1901-1937 (Box 23)
    - James Gillespie Blaine Ewing (Box 24)
      - From Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing, 1897-1908 (Box 24)
      - To Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing, 1891-1936 (Box 24)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1887-1937 (Box 24)
    - "Miscellaneous I" (Box 24)
    - "Miscellaneous II" (Box 24)
  - Correspondence (Box 25)
    - Charles Ewing (1872-1954) to Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing (Box 25)
      - 1894-1930, (4 vols.) (Box 25)
      - 1932-1937, (2 vols.) (Box 26)
    - Virginia Miller Ewing Anderson (Box 26)
      - To Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing (Box 26)
        - 1890-1891 (Box 26)
        - 1891-1902, (2 vols.) (Box 27)
      - To various persons, 1895-1951 (Box 27)
    - Maria Ewing to Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing, 1888-1937, (2 vols.) (Box 28)
    - John Krepps Miller Ewing to Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing, 1893-1930, (2 vols.) (Box 28)
    - Kathleen Ewing Daly to Virginia Larwill Miller Ewing, 1891-1937, (2 vols.) (Box 29)
- Miscellany, 1865 (Box 30)
  Genealogical notebook and photograph album of Civil War army officers.
  - Genealogical notebook, "Neil Gillespie of 'Indian Hill,' Washington, County, Penn.," undated (Box 30)
  - Photograph album inscribed to "Mrs. M. E. Steele from her brother Charles Ewing. Lancaster O, 10th of Aug 1865," 1865 (Box 30)
- Oversize, 1777-1941 (Box OV 1)
  Scrapbook containing originals and copies of military commissions, correspondence, diplomas, and other documents.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - Scrapbook (Box OV 1)
    - Charles Ewing (1835-1883), Thomas Ewing (1789-1871), and George Ewing (1754-1824), 1777-1941 (Container 16) (Box OV 1)